Guide to the William Mason Autographs of Musicians
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
William Mason Autographs of Musicians,
1830-1906
Mason, William, 1829-1908, collector.
103 items (1 v.)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079084
Biographical Note
Pianist, teacher, and musical theoretician.
Scope and Content
This collection of autographed inscriptions and letters from noted 19th century musicians was assembled by Mason. The material includes the signatures of 85 composer, performers, and other musical people, most of whom were Dr. Mason's contemporaries and personal friends. There are 103 items the majority of which are bits of music in script with signatures, and a few autograph letters to Mason. Among those represented are Berlioz, Jenny Lind, Franz Liszt, MacDowell, Paderewski, Rubinstein, Saint-Saens, Samaroff, and the Schumanns.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 1 series:
X780. M38. Folio
Subjects
Berlioz, Hector, 1803-1869.; Lind, Jenny, 1820-1887.; Liszt, Franz, 1811-1886.; MacDowell, Edward, 1860-1908.; Paderewski, Ignace Jan, 1860-1941.; Rubinstein, Anton, 1829-1894.; Saint-Saëns, Camille, 1835-1921.; Samaroff Stokowski, Olga, 1882-1948.; Schumann, Robert, 1810-1856.; Schumann, Clara, 1819-1896.; Musicians.; Composers.; Music theory.; Autographs.; Teachers.; Pianists.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
Van Sindern, Mina Mason Gift
- X780. M38. Folio
  Available on microfilm. Signed "William Mason, Orange, N.J., Nov. 15, 1883" on page 1. Book is paginated 1-101
  - Ander, Alios Heidenroslein, 3 May 1851, (1 page score) (Folder 2)
  - Aus der Ohe, Adele Score, New York, May 1897, (1 page) (Folder 3)
  - Bachmann, Caroline Listesfotempo, (1 page score) (Folder 4)
  - Benedict, Julius Score, London, 30 May 1853, (1 page) (Folder 5)
  - Berlioz, Hector Score, [April or May 1854], (1 page) (Folder 6)
  - Brandeis, Johann Note, Prague, 20 May 1851, (1 page) (Folder 7)
    [Includes portrait]
  - Brockway, Howard Score, New York, 20 October 1899, (1 page) (Folder 8)
  - Brodsky, Adolf Score, New York, 22 February 1892, (1 page) (Folder 9)
  - Buck, Dudley Signarure, [n.p.], 13 February 1894, (1 page) (Folder 10)
  - Bull, Ole Bornemann Signature, Astor House New York, 19 November 1845, (1 page (fragment)) (Folder 11)
  - Bulow, Hans von To William Mason, Boston, 21 October 1875, (2 page a.l.s.) (Folder 12)
  - Cossmann, Bernhard The Spleen, New York, 26 May 1876, (2 page score) (Folder 13)
  - Carreno, Teresa, 1853-1917 Score and note, New York, 1897, (1 page) (Folder 14)
  - Drevschock, Alexander and Raimund Score and note, Prague and Leipzig, 1851 and 1856, (1 page) (Folder 15)
  - Essipoff, Annette Score and note, New York, 18 May 1877, (1 page) (Folder 16)
  - Friedheim, Arthur Maestoso Trionfante, New York, 20 December 1894, (1 page score, with note) (Folder 17)
  - Gabrilowitsch, Ossip Minuet, New York, 11 November 1900, (1 page score, with note) (Folder 18)
  - Godowsky, Leopold Moto Perpetuo, [n.p.], 7 March 1899, (1 page score, with note) (Folder 19)
  - Goldbeck, Robert Fragment of letter, St. Louis, 11 June 1883, (1 page) (Folder 20)
  - Gottschalk, Louis Moreau To William Mason, [New York], [n.d.], (1 page a.l.s.) (Folder 21)
  - Gridley, C. E. To William Mason, Hamburg, 5 August 1849, (1 page a.l.s.) (Folder 22)
  - Grieg, Edvard Score, [Bergen Norway], [1 July 1890], (1 page) (Folder 23)
  - Haberbier, Ernst Score, London, 30 May 1853, (1 page ) (Folder 24)
  - Hauptmann, Moritz Score, with note, Leipzig, 1850, (1 page ) (Folder 25)
  - Huss, Henry Holden Score, with letter, [n.p.], 27 March 1875, (1 page a.l.s.) (Folder 26)
  - Joachim, Joseph Score, Leipzig, 29 June 1850, (1 page) (Folder 27)
  - Joseffy, Rafael Score, with note, New York, August 1889, (1 page) (Folder 28)
  - Klindworth, Carl Score, with note, Germany, 9 February 1854, (1 page) (Folder 29)
  - Kneisel Quartet Note with drawing, New York, 4 April 1899, (1 page) (Folder 30)
  - Kubelik, Jan Mendelssohn, 1901, (1 page score, with note) (Folder 31)
  - Laub, Ferdinand To Mr. Ella[?], [n.p.], [n.d.], (2 page a.l.s.) (Folder 32)
  - Laub, Ferdinand Etude, Austria, 15 June 1853, (1 page score) (Folder 33)
  - Leschetizky, Theodor To William Mason, Austria, 9 May 1897, (4 page a.l.s.) (Folder Pages 34 & 35)
    [Page 35 contains a typed (carbon) transcription of the a.l.s.]
  - Lind, Jenny [To George Webb], New York, 17 September 1850, (2 page a.l.s.) (Folder 36)
  - Liszt, Franz To William Mason, [v.p.], 19 August 1849 - 23 March 1880, (7 a.l.s.) (Folder Pages 37 - 45)
  - Liszt, Franz Score, [n.p.], 28 August 1849, (1 page) (Folder 46)
  - Handel E minor Fugue, Austria, [ca. 1850], (1 page printed score) (Folder 47)
    [Pencil marks by Listz]
  - MacDowell, Edward Score, with note, [n.p.], 13 December 1894, (1 page) (Folder 48)
  - Rosenberg, C. Portrait of Mary Webb Mason [wife of William Mason], [n.p.], 1 March 1860, (1 page) (Folder 49)
  - Mayer, Carl Score, Hamburg, 25 January 1849, (1 page) (Folder 50)
  - Mills, Sebastian Bach Score, [n.p.], 20 May 1873, (1 page) (Folder 51)
  - Moor, Emanuel Score, New York, 14 September, () (Folder 52)
  - Szumowska, Antoinette Chopin Nocturne, New York, 19 May 1895, (1 page) (Folder 52r)
  - Fontaine, Mortier de Fugue, Hambourg, 28 July 1859, (1 page) (Folder 53)
  - Moscheles, Ignaz [To William Mason], Leipzig, 22 May 1850, (2 page a.l.s.) (Folder 54)
  - Moscheles, Ignaz Exercise, Leipzig, 8 February 1850, (1 page score) (Folder 55)
  - Moscheles, Ignaz [To William Mason], [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 page a.n.s.) (Folder 56)
  - Paderewski, Ignaz Score, New York, 21 December 1891, (1 page ) (Folder 57)
  - Dohnanyi, Ernst von Score, New York, 12 April 1900, (1 page ) (Folder 57r)
  - Paine, John Knowles Score, with note, Appledore NH, August 1855, (1 page ) (Folder 58)
  - Paur, Emil Score, with note, New York, [1897?], (1 page ) (Folder 59)
  - Pruckner, Dionys Score, Weimar, 26 June [n.y.], (1 page ) (Folder 60)
  - Raff, Joachim Transcription for piano, Weimar, 25 June 1854, (1 page ) (Folder 61)
  - Raff, Joachim [To William Mason], Frankfurt, 16 January 1880, (1 page a.l.s.) (Folder 62)
  - Rea, William Score, Leipzig, 11 January 1850, (1 page) (Folder 63)
  - Hauptmanns, Moritz Engraved portrait, Leipzig, 31 December 1868, (1 page) (Folder 63r)
  - Reissiger, Karl Gottlieb Score, Dresden, 4 May 1850, () (Folder 64)
  - Remenyi, Eduard Score, with note, New York, 3 January 1895, (1 page) (Folder 65)
  - Richter, Ernst Friedrich Score, Leipzig, 14 May 1850, (1 page) (Folder 66)
  - Rubinstein, Anton Score, Weimar, 5 June 1854, (1 page) (Folder 67)
  - Safonoff, Vassily Quote, with note, [n.p.], 31 January 1906, (1 page) (Folder 68)
  - Samaroff, Olga Note, [n.p.], 9 March 1906, (1 page) (Folder 69)
  - Saint-Saens, Camille To Randolph Brodsky, Paris, 27 February 1889, (2 page a.l.s., 1 visiting card) (Folder 70)
  - Schindler, Anton Score, Frankfurt, 30 September 1852, (1 page) (Folder 71)
  - Schneider, Johann Score, Dresden, 3 May 1850, (1 page) (Folder 72)
  - Schnyder von Wartensee, Xaver Score, with note, [n.p.], 1853, (2 pages) (Folder Pages 73 & 73r)
  - Schulhoff, Jules Scherzo, Prague, 26 Septmeber 1850, (1 page score) (Folder 74)
  - Schumann, Clara Score, Dresden, 30 April 1850, (1 page) (Folder 75)
  - Schumann, Robert Score, Dresden, 29 April 1850, (1 page) (Folder 76)
  - Sembrich, Marcella Marriage of Figgaro, [n.p.], 7 October 1915, (1 page score fragment) (Folder 77)
  - Siloti, Alexander Score fragment, with note, New York, 22 March 1898, (1 page) (Folder 78)
  - Hambourg, Mark Note with score fragment, [n.p.], 23 November 1899, (1 page) (Folder 78r)
  - Sivori, Camillo Score, Boston, 13 November 1846, (1 page) (Folder 79)
  - Slivinski, Joseph Score, New York, 20 April 1899, (1 page) (Folder 80)
  - Sontag, Henriette Score, Munchen, 22 May 1852, (1 page) (Folder 81)
  - Stavenhagen, Bernhard Score, with note, New York, 1 May 1895, (1 page) (Folder 82)
  - Sternberg, Constantin I.E. von Score, with note, New York, 15 June 1897, (1 page) (Folder 83)
  - Sudlatzek, Mary Score, with note, 29 July 1851, ( 1 page) (Folder 84)
  - Sudlatzek, Theresa To William Mason, 29 July 1851, (2 page a.l.s.) (Folder Pages 85 & 85r)
  - Tchaikovsky, Piotr Ilyich To Brodsky, [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 page a.l.s.) (Folder 86)
  - Berlioz, Hector Photograph and etching of, [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 page) (Folder 87)
  - Vieuxtemps, Henri Score, Weimar, 19 April 1854, (1 page) (Folder 87r)
  - Thomas, Christian Friedrich Theodore (1835-1905) To Willaim Mason, New York, 12 March 1881, (1 page a.l.s.) (Folder 88)
  - Fiske, John and Celia Thaxter Drawing and Greek quote, Isle of Sholas, 4 September 1887 & 28 July 1888, (1 page) (Folder 89)
  - Thalberg, Sigismond Score, with note, [n.p.], 21 October 1856, (1 page) (Folder 90)
  - Wagner, Richard Score, with note, Zurich, 5 June 1852, (1 page) (Folder 91)
  - Whiting, Arthur Score, with note, New York, 5 March 1895, (1 page) (Folder 92)
  - Wilhelmj, August Score, with note, New York, 26 November 1878, (1 page) (Folder 93)
  - Willmers, Rudolph La Pompa di Festa, Vienna, 14 August 1850, (1 page) (Folder 94)
  - Wolf, Carl Maria Score, Berlin, 6 April 1852, (1 page) (Folder 95)
  - Mason, William Autographs from Album which are especially interesting to me in the "Book of 'Memories' etc.", New York, [n.d.], (3 page a.ms. list) (Folder 101)